Good morning. So today's דף daf is דף נ"ד daf nun daled
and we pick up about
let's pick up with
one, two, three, six lines from the top, ובחוזר. Ubechozer. And what
we are doing—oh look it didn't get erased—what we're doing is we're
looking at the two פסוקים pesukim that talk about טומאת מת tumat
met and what we learn from the different words in the פסוקים.
pesukim. And in particular because we want to understand what things are
מטמא באוהל metameh b'ohel and what things are
there's not enough of it to cause טומאה tumah as it were,
this quantity in an אוהל, ohel, but it is through direct touch.
And both of the פסוקים pesukim in the פשט pshat are talking
about touch: וכל אשר יגע על פני השדה—and Vechol asher yigah al
p'nei hasadeh on the open field means specifically not under a roof,
so it's not טומאת אוהל. tumat ohel. And then ועל הנוגע—both ve'al
hanogaya of them seem to be talking about touch. But what these
מדרשי הלכה midreshei halakha that we looked at say is that על
פני השדה al p'nei hasadeh somehow means you're over the face of
the מת, met, you're like leaning over it and you're not exactly
touching it and it's talking about אוהל, ohel, the sides that this
פסוק pasuk is talking about אוהל. ohel. And therefore we learn all
these things: חלל חרב מת עצם אדם וקבר chalal cherev met etzem
adam vekover are things that cause טומאה tumah in the אוהל. ohel.
Not...
so חלל chalal somehow is understood to mean a thing that is
sort of has been an אבר מן החי, eiver min hachai, a
limb that's been severed from a person—there's not an entire corpse, but
this is something that itself is dead. חרב Cherev is a very
important הלכה halakha which we're going to get to today, which is
חרב הרי הוא כחלל. cherev harei hu kechalal. The sword is like
the corpse itself. This means the corpse is an אבי אבות הטומאה,
avi avot hatumah, so the person who touches it is an אב,
av, not a ראשון, rishon, and is טמא tamei for seven days.
So a sword also has the same הלכה halakha and a person
who touches a sword—I'm putting sort of quote marks—whatever הלכה halakha we're
going to define means
חרב—is... cherev the sword is considered the אבי אבות avi avot and
the person who touches it is an אב av and is טמא
tamei for seven days. Now what constitutes a חרב? cherev? That is
going to be a major debate of the ראשונים rishonim in today's
דף. daf. It is basically some... not doesn't have to be a
sword, it's abstracted, but it starts with the possibility of all metal
vessels and it might even include all vessels. Okay, so we're going
to see what that is. And if a חרב cherev comes טומאת
מת, tumat met, it actually goes... is an אבי אבות הטומאה. avi
avot hatumah. Maybe it's worth mentioning about this, a parallel to another
area of הלכה halakha where something does not go down a level
because of its more identity rather than its contact. And that's the
idea of the משכב ומושב mishkav u'moshav of a זב. zav. א
זב A zav is an אב הטומאה—okay, av hatumah maybe it's an
אבי אבות, avi avot, one level higher or whatever—but a זב zav
is an אב הטומאה. av hatumah. If a זב zav or a
זבה zavah or נדה niddah sits on something, it's called a משכב
mishkav or a מושב, moshav, and that is not a ראשון. rishon.
A normal vessel that touches a זב zav or a person that
touches a זב zav is a ראשון. rishon. But the thing that
a זב zav sits on and he doesn't even have to come
in contact with it—it could be a series of cushions, like the
princess and the pea, right—it could be like the tenth cushion below
him and that's called his seat, and that's also an אב הטומאה
av hatumah by its identity as the seat of a זב. zav.
So that's another sort of source of an אב הטומאה av hatumah
and it's not this normal sense that it goes down a level
through the process of contact. In some similar conceptual way, a חרב—now
cherev if it really was the sword that killed somebody, maybe you
could understand that as meaningful and has status like something that was
sat on—but we're going to wind up abstracting it. Okay, at this
level let's say metal vessels that were טומאת מת—either tumat met under
the same roof or touched a dead body—are conceptualized as חרב cherev
and are an אבי אבות הטומאה avi avot hatumah just like the
מת. met. So it's called חרב הרי הוא כחלל. cherev harei hu
kechalal. More about that a little bit later today. מת Met again,
somehow all of this is understood to be talking about something out
of the ordinary, not a normal corpse. So if חלל chalal is
something that is been dead limb but not a dead person, מת
met is also a limb but an אבר מן המת. eiver min
hamet. And that's מטמא באוהל. metameh b'ohel. עצם אדם Etzem adam is
a bone, but here and particularly in the area of bones is
where we find a difference between the amount that causes טומאה tumah
in an אוהל ohel and the amount that's cause טומאה tumah through
touch. And the difference here is עצם אדם etzem adam as opposed
to עצם. etzem. So the way I understand it—this wasn't spelled out
in the מדרשי הלכה midreshei halakha but this is what I understand
what's being done is—it has to be enough bone that represents the
entire person. So that would be, you know, רוב מנין, rov minyan,
רוב בנין, rov binyan, a שדרה, shidrah, גולגולת, gulgoret, or a certain
quantity that comes from those amounts of bones—that's עצם אדם. etzem adam.
And קבר kover is the... is the grave itself and that we
said is the reason why graveyards are a problem because why don't
you just say—not the grave, the coffin—why don't you just say that
the coffin is a טומאת אוהל tumat ohel and just stops the
טומאה? tumah? And the answer is, is because this principle of קבר
סתום kever satum says if the coffin is sealed on all sides,
the walls and the top, then the entire coffin is treated as
the מת met itself and the טומאה tumah goes up and... And
therefore it's מטמא metamei not just כנגד kineged the מת meis but
כנגד kineged the entire directly opposite the entire coffin and the coffin
doesn't serve as an אוהל. ohel. So that's very important. This is
the reason why we really have problems with the graveyards and we
don't say that the coffin serves as an אוהל. ohel. So those
are the things that cause טומאה באוהל. tuma be'ohel. Okay, so that's
very important that that's the basis of the פסוק. pasuk. Now we're
going to look at this next פסוק pasuk which seems to be
pretty much the same terms, and we're going to say that that's
telling you things that are טומאה tuma through touch and not through
אוהל. ohel. So what are going to be those different things? Okay,
so עצם etzem is the most obvious difference. Here it's עצם אדם
etzem adam and here it's עצם. etzem. So even a small amount
of bone, the size of a barley grain, is through touch. That's
the major place where there's a difference between טומאת אוהל tumas ohel
and טומאת מגע tumas maga is bones. Now how about חלל chalal
and מת? meis? You'll remember here חלל chalal and מת meis were
אבר מן החי eiver min hachai and אבר מן המת. eiver min
hameis. So this ברייתא braisa is the ברייתא braisa that supports ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish who says you can have an אבר מן החי
eiver min hachai and אבר מן המת eiver min hameis that are
מטמא במגע metamei bemaga and not באוהל. be'ohel. So this אבר מן
החי eiver min hachai and אבר מן המת eiver min hameis have
enough flesh on it that if it were attached to a person
the limb could survive. And this is אבר מן החי eiver min
hachai and אבר מן המת eiver min hameis that do not have
enough flesh on it. And ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says: Here's my
proof. This ברייתא braisa shows that there is such a thing as
אבר מן החי eiver min hachai and אבר מן המת eiver min
hameis without enough flesh on it that still cause טומאה tuma through
touch. And again if there was enough bone, if there was עצם
כשעורה etzem kese'orah that would be the טומאה tuma of bone. So
it must be that there's not enough bone, there's not enough flesh,
but because it still is a limb it still causes contact through
touch. And that was the debate of רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan and
ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, and ריש לקיש Reish Lakish supports himself based
on that ברייתא. braisa. So let's take questions. Let's just read that
ברייתא braisa together and then if there's any questions I'll take it.
Okay, so ואילו v'ilu let's start again from two lines from the
top on נד עמוד ב. nun daled amud beis. ואילו גבי נגיעה
v'ilu gabi negiah when it comes to touch אמר רב יהודה תניא.
amar Rav Yehuda tanya. רב יהודה Rav Yehuda says we
taught in a ברייתא: braisa: ועל הנוגע v'al hanogea בעצם או בחלל.
be'etzem o vechalal. בעצם—זה עצם כשעורה. etzem kese'orah, או בחלל—זה אבר הנחלם
מן החי, so something that has been
severed and from a live person, ואין בו להעלות ארוחה, v'ein bo
lehaalos arucha, there's not enough flesh that it could heal were it
attached. או במת—זה אבר הנחלם מן המת. Okay. או בקבר o vekevor
and קבר kevor which is the last one we haven't dealt with.
זה קבר—אמר ריש לקיש: Reish Lakish זה קבר שלפני הדיבור. zeh kevor
shelifnei hadibur. This is the קבר kevor before the divine speech. Now
I'm going to bracket that for a second. That's very fascinating. But
I'm going to bracket that just to get to the end of
the argument and then we'll go back to the קבר. kevor. So
האי אבר מן המת היכי דמי? hai eiver min hameis heichi dami?
So this ברייתא braisa then includes an אבר מן המת eiver min
hameis that causes טומאה tuma through touch. What's the case? אי דאית
ביה עצם כשעורה, ei de'is beih etzem kese'orah, if there's enough bone
in it, היינו הנוגע בעצם, hainu hanogea be'etzem, that's bone. אלא דלית
ביה עצם כשעורה, ela deleis beih etzem kese'orah, then it must be
that it's not enough bone. It's a limb, not enough bone to
cause טומאה, tuma, not enough flesh to heal, and nevertheless, again I
don't know what limb we're talking about, but nevertheless because it's a
limb it causes טומאה tuma through touch, ואפילו הכי רחמנא רבייה. v'afillu
hachi rachmana rabyei. The תורה Torah is including it. So you see
that even though, and remember the point was that when it said
things that a נזיר nazir is מגלח, megaleach, it only mentioned a
limb with enough flesh. It never mentioned in אוהל ohel or touch
a limb without enough flesh. But ריש לקיש says even though that's
what the משנה mishna sounds like, the מדרש הלכה midrash halacha make
it clear that a limb without enough flesh causes טומאת מת tumas
meis and I'm going to assume therefore that a נזיר nazir is
going to be מגלח megaleach if he touches it. Not for אוהל,
ohel, but if he touches it. Let's read רבי יוחנן's Rebbi Yochanan
response and then I'll take questions. אמר לך רבי יוחנן. amar lach
Rebbi Yochanan. רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan would say back: לעולם דאית ביה.
le'olam de'is beih. It is there is enough bone in it for
נוגע בעצם. nogea be'etzem. It's עצם כשעורה, etzem kese'orah. that's that ברייתא.
braisa. ואי אינו עניין למגע, v'ei eino inyan lemaga, תנהו עניין למשא.
tanehu inyan lemassa. So why does it have to be mentioned if
this has enough bone, so we already said עצם, etzem, enough bone.
So it's to tell you that not only because we dealt here
with two types of טומאה: tuma: touching and we've decided that this
was אוהל. ohel. There's a third type of way you become טמא
במת: tamei bemeis: not you don't touch it, you're not in the
same אוהל ohel or you're not on top or below it, but
you're carrying it. Okay, that's a lot in the תורה, Torah, it
talks about somebody who carries טומאה. tuma. So where does that fall?
So you know is carrying and we know as we've said before
if it was in the משנה, mishna, carrying is like touching, right?
So if it's enough to cause טומאה tuma through touch, it's enough
through carrying. But where do we get that from?
So says רבי יוחנן, Rebbi Yochanan, you know what? In the end
this really is just a variation of עצם כשעורה. That's really the
only area where touching is different than אוהל ohel is by bones.
Okay, not... I don't agree with רב סוצקי *Rav Sotsky*'s shtick there's
a second דין *din* of אבר *ever*. This is really just another
variation of עצם *etzem*. Why does it say it again? To tell
you that it's not only through touch, it's even through carrying. Okay,
so that's the debate of רב יוחנן וריש לקיש *Rav Yochanan v'Reish
Lakish*. That's where we get it from the פסוקים *psukim*. And that's
the question of אבר מן החי *ever min hachai* that does not
have enough flesh is still enough of an object of טומאה tumah,
*tumah* to cause טומאה tumah *tumah* through touch. Now question? Yes.
Where is this? Is it in a משנה mishnah *mishnah*? It says
in אהלות *Ohalot*, but then it says חולין *Chullin*, it's introduced by
תניא *tanya*.
Yeah, it's a משנה mishnah *mishnah* in אהלות *Ohalot*. You see that?
What? The אמר מר *amar mar*, that was what we didn't start
with, that was from the end of yesterday, טומאה tumah, בוקעת ועולה
בוקעת ויורדת *tumah boka'at v'olah boka'at v'yoredet*. So that's אהלות פרק ז'
משנה mishnah. א' *Ohalot perek zayin mishnah aleph*, and it's cross-referenced in
חולין *Chullin*, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* in חולין *Chullin* quotes it.
But when you call that מדרש *midrash*, that's also מדרש הלכה Midrash
Halacha, *Midrash Halacha*.
No, no, that תוספתא *Tosefta*, it's a תניא *tanya*, the תוספתא *Tosefta*,
excuse me, the מדרש הלכה midrash halacha. *Midrash Halacha* that interpreted this
פסוק pasuk *pasuk* was introduced by תניא *tanya* in the previous ברייתא
*braita*. The גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* then at the end of that, when
it mentioned חרב cherev *cherev*, quoted a משנה mishnah *mishnah* of בוקעת
ועולה *boka'at v'olah*. Okay, but the basic ברייתא *braita* that darshened this
was מדרש הלכה halacha *Midrash Halacha*, okay? And the same that the
basic ברייתא *braita* that darshened this is a מדרש הלכה *Midrash Halacha*.
Although not in this... yeah, go ahead.
And from the מדרש *midrash* on the חרב *cherev* that conceptualizes כלים
*keilim* as אבי אבות הטומאה avi avos hatumah *avi
avot hatumah*, yeah,
would you say that חז"ל *Chazal* are conceptualizing human manufactured vessels the
same way that they're conceptualizing the body that הקדוש ברוך הוא *Hakadosh
Baruch Hu* has created?
There's a link between vessels and the body. Well, but the problem
is that a person that touches the מת meis *met* is not
an אבי אבות avi avos *avi avot*, he's only an אב av,
*av*. So the vessels is a different status here. But I do
think it is true that vessels and people, you know, have sort
of like similar areas of טומאה tumah? *tumah*. When you get to
a שני *sheni*, the only thing that can become a שני *sheni*
is like food, not people and vessels. So they tend to be
within the same category. But I wouldn't read that into this, because
here it's actually worse, you know, in terms of its level of
טומאה tumah *tumah*, than a person who touches the dead body. Yes.
So two things then. Where where ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish* learns טומאת
tumath משא *tumat massa* from?
Yeah, I don't know.
And the other part, can you conceptually see a difference between, like,
you know, the עצם *etzem* is like, you know, what it sounds
like, actually touching the עצם *etzem*. But for the flesh, you know,
to say that's also טומאת עצם *tumat etzem*, I mean you aren't
necessarily...
yeah, I understand, what can I tell you, it's a classic thing,
you know, the גמרא gemara *Gemara* does אם אינו ענין לזה, תנהו
ענין לזה *im eino inyan l'zeh, tnehu inyan l'zeh*. I mean I
can't get too excited about that.
Yes. When we were talking about טומאת אוהל ohel, *tumat ohel* when
you say שדרה וגולגולת *shidrah v'gulgoret*, do you need both or just
more than one area actually?
So that was all of yesterday's דף daf, *daf*. So get the
notes from somebody who was here in class yesterday. Okay, in the
end of the day, the גמרא gemara *Gemara* doesn't explicitly conclude, but
all the evidence points to one or the other, and that's the
way the רמב"ם *Rambam* rules. Okay, so now let's get back to
this fascinating phrase of קבר kever לפני הדיבור *kever lifnei hadibbur*, before
the divine speech. So what does that mean? So let's take a
look at תוספות Tosfos *Tosafot*. תוספות Tosfos *Tosafot* gives two possibilities. או
בקבר, o bakever. אמר ריש לקיש amar Reish Lakish: אמר זה קבר
zeh kevor שלפני הדיבור *O bakever, amar Reish Lakish amar zeh kever
she-lifnei ha-dibbur*, שקודם מתן תורה Matan Torah
*she-kodem matan Torah*. וצריך עיון *v'tzarich iyun*, לרבנן ורבי שמעון דאמרי אף
קברי עובדי כוכבים מטמאים באוהל *lerabbanan v'Rabbi Shimon d'amri af kivrei ovdei
kochavim metamm'im b'ohel*, דלא דרשינן אתם אתם קרויים אדם *d'lo darshinan atem
atem keruyim adam*, okay, which is a very difficult דרשה drasha *drasha*.
Let's bracket that for now. אמאי איצטריך *amai itztarich* או בקבר *o
bakever*? Why או בקבר *o bakever* if your position is that non-Jews
cause טומאת אוהל ohel. *tumat ohel*? So what is he getting at?
Whoever discussed non-Jews? So it seems that the way תוספות Tosfos *Tosafot*
is understanding it is before מתן תורה Matan Torah *Matan Torah*, basically,
this is a, you know, we all had a status of non-Jews.
Well, I mean that would be a little anachronistic. We didn't have
a status yet of ישראל *Yisrael*. This is an interesting question, right?
When do we shift from בני נח *bnei Noach* to a status
of ישראל *Yisrael*? This is פרשת נח *Parshat Noach*. When do we
shift from בני נח *bnei Noach* to a status of ישראל *Yisrael*,
right? Is it from the moment אברהם *Avraham* is given ברית מילה
*brit milah*? Is it from מעמד הר סיני Har Sinai. *ma'amad Har
Sinai*? There's a whole book written by, I think, the משנה mishnah
למלך *Mishneh Lamelech*, called פרשת דרכים *Parshat Drachim*, that he works through
all of these מדרשים *midrashim* through this lens of seeing that it
was a מחלוקת *machloket*, you know, like reading this, like, anachronistically, this
מחלוקת *machloket* of when did בני ישראל *bnei Yisrael* have that status.
The whole debate of יוסף והאחים *Yosef v'ha-achim*, so they told on
him they ate אבר מן החי *ever min hachai*, was really cause
יוסף *Yosef* thought he had a status of בני ישראל *bnei Yisrael*
and they thought he had a status of בני נח *bnei Noach*.
Anyway, so this is an interesting question of when do we holistically
get that status. תוספות Tosfos *Tosafot* seems to be understanding that the
point of לפני הדיבור *lifnei ha-dibbur* is, you know, if you assume
that טומאת אוהל *tumat ohel* is only for ישראל *Yisrael* and not
for בני נח *bnei Noach*, so what would be the status of
טומאת אוהל *tumat ohel* before מתן תורה Torah *Matan Torah*? Okay, and
let's say somebody, I don't know, who walked over, you know, was
in the same tent as a dead body before מתן תורה *Matan
Torah*, when it came to מתן תורה *Matan Torah*, are they טהור
tahor, *tahor* or are they טמא tamei *tamei*? Okay, what's their status?
What was the status of that, wait a minute, before מתן תורה
*Matan Torah*? So תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* says, but you wouldn't need a
פסוק pasuk, *pasuk* to say that you're טמא tamei *tamei* if you
already say that non-Jews are מטמא באוהל mitamei b'ohel, *metamme b'ohel*. So
I don't understand why you need the פסוק *posuk* to say you're
טמא tamei, *tamei* if you were in, if there, if you were
in the same, if you were in the same אהל ohel. *ohel*
as a dead body before מתן תורה *Matan Torah*, if it's true
even about non-Jews? So why should it be any different? So he
doesn't understand why. Okay, so presumably though he understood the דרשה drasha
*drasha* that if non-Jews are not מטמא mitamei. באהל *metamei b'ohel*, what
this או בקבר קבר kever, לפני הדיבור *o b'kever kever lifnei hadibbor*
saying is, but a Jew before מתן תורה *Matan Torah* would be
מטמא באהל *metamei b'ohel*. Non-Jews no, but Jews before מתן תורה *Matan
Torah* yes. But if you say non-Jews are also מטמא באהל *metamei
b'ohel*, why do you need the דרשה *drasha*?
But you say we became Jews מתן תורה *Matan Torah*, there were
no Jews before מתן תורה *Matan Torah*.
Okay, but whatever, בני אברהם יצחק ויעקב *Bnei Avraham Yitzchak v'Yaakov*, yes.
The גמרא gemara *Gemara* in סנהדרין *Sanhedrin* actually uses the...
Or maybe that's what it's telling you.
Yes, they actually use the אבות *Avos* to derive Noachide laws.
Yes, right, so that's a whole, it's a whole fascinating right תורה
*Torah* around all of that. But that seems to be implicit in
what תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* is saying. But if non-Jews already are מטמא
באהל *metamei b'ohel*, what is קבר kever, לפני הדיבור *kever lifnei hadibbor*
telling you here? ויש לומר דרבי שמעוני *V'yesh lomar d'Rabbi Shimoni*. Okay,
so fine, it is רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* who says non-Jews no,
but לפני הדיבור *lifnei hadibbor* yes. מיהו קשה דהא לגבי נגיעה מודה
רבי שמעון דכי עובדי כוכבים מטמאי במגע ובמשא *Mihu kasha d'ha lagabi
negiah modeh Rabbi Shimon d'ki ovdei kochavim mitamei b'maga u'v'massa*. We know
that, and I've mentioned this before, that through touch they are מטמא
*metamei*. This is why the whole thing about כהנים kohanim *Kohanim* becoming
doctors, it's not enough to say maybe they're not Jews, the corpses
are from non-Jews, because
the difference is only a difference really of אהל ohel. *ohel*, it's
not a difference of touch. Okay, דהא גבי נגיעה מודה רבי שמעון
דכי עובדי כוכבים מטמאי במגע ובמשא כדאמר רבינא בפרק הבא על יבמתו
*d'ha gabi negiah modeh Rabbi Shimon d'ki ovdei kochavim mitamei b'maga u'v'massa
k'd'amar Ravina b'perek Ha-Ba al Yevimto*. ודוחק לומר דלא כרבינא *V'dochek lomar
d'lo k'Ravina*. So he says but nevertheless it's still through נגיעה *negiah*,
so I'm not exactly sure, wait, what's his question?
What's
his question? Because this is still a פסוק *posuk* about אהל ohel
*ohel*. דהכא גבי נגיעה כתיב
*D'hacha gabi negiah ksiv*. Oh, because I'm sorry, right, because we're not
this קבר *kever*. This קבר *kever* is קבר סתום kever satum *kever
satum*. Like this קבר *kever* by אהל ohel. *ohel*, we learned that
קבר סתום kever satum, *kever satum*. We're talking about this קבר *kever*.
That's the one thing we didn't דרש *darsh*. This קבר *kever* we
say, what happened, it started already one second. We say that this
is קבר לפני הדיבור *kever lifnei hadibbor*. And that's about touch, right?
This is the פסוק *posuk* about touch we're learning קבר לפני הדיבור
*kever lifnei hadibbor*. So he says by touch, presumably everybody agrees non-Jews
are מטמא *metamei* through touch, so why do you need a חידוש
chiddush *chiddush* of קבר לפני הדיבור *kever lifnei hadibbor*? That's his question.
So let's see.
Even though it's before דיבור *dibbor*, you're still טמא tamei. *tamei*, because
we...
So maybe what you're saying is, maybe it doesn't have to do
with the status of the person, Jew, non-Jew, it has to do
with the fact before the law is legislated. Excellent. So that's the
next thing תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* says, which is I probably, what would
be the more natural. It's not about the person, it's about what,
does the law, are you grandfathered in, as it were? You know,
what's the status if you encountered that before the legislation? Could also
be an interesting question, right? To what degree do you think all
these things of טומאה וטהרה tumah vetaharah? *tumah v'tahara* are metaphysical realities
or are they just הלכה *halacha*? If they're just הלכה *halacha*, before
it's been legislated, it doesn't exist. Okay, so let's take a look.
והריצב"א פירש קבר שלפני הדיבור גם אותם שמתו קודם מתן תורה קודם
שנאמרה פרשת או שבא לאחר מתן תורה *V'haRitzba peirush kever she-lifnei hadibbor
gam osam she-meisu kodem Matan Torah kodem she-ne'emra parshas o she-ba l'achar
Matan Torah*. I think he switches it to... קודם לאחר מתן תורה
*kodem l'achar Matan Torah*. It doesn't matter, it's after מתן תורה *Matan
Torah*. We're all Jews. But you know what דיבור *dibbor* hasn't occurred
yet? The פרשה parsha *parsha* of טומאת מת tumas meis *tumos meis*.
Right? That דיבור *dibbor*, the very specific one! So everyone has the
status of Jews, we just haven't yet been מצווה *metzuveh* on טומאת
מת tumas meis *tumos meis*. It hasn't yet, up until the story
with מדין *Midyan* and with אדם כי ימות באהל *adam ki yamut
b'ohel*, that פרשה parsha *parsha*, it's way in חוקת *Chukas*, that פרשה
*parsha* hasn't occurred yet. Okay. דסלקא דעתך אמינא אדם כי ימות באהל
מפרשה זו ואילך desalka daitach amina adam ki yamut be’ohel miparsha zu
va’eilaich. *D'salka dachach amina adam ki yamut b'ohel miparsah zu v'ilech*. From
this point on. So what happens if you came into contact with
it? Now, of course the funny thing is, is that the whole
problem with the פסח שני Pesach Sheini. *Pesach Sheni* was that אנחנו
טמאים לנפש אדם *anachnu tmeiyim l'nefesh adam* and so on. So but
that wasn't a קבר *kever*. Maybe there were some laws of טומאת
מת tumas meis. *tumos meis* that applied before, but some that were
מתחדש *mischadesh* now. Maybe they should only be applying from now on.
Maybe קבר *kever* is only from this point on. Certainly קבר סתום
kever satum, *kever satum*, which is a new הלכה *halacha* or something,
I don't know. So he says in a
matter of several months.
Right. ואמרו...
לא, איפה... *V'amru... lo, eifo...* פרשת חוקת *Parshat
Chukas*.
Where is that? Isn't that towards the end of the ארבעים שנה
*arba'im shana*? Isn't that right before מדין *Midyan*? No, am I misremembering?
חוקת *Chukas* has a 40-year gap in it, yeah. And the thing
with מדין *Midyan* was towards the end of it.
Beginning of חוקת *Chukas*, we have a Bible scholar here. Dr. Fishbein,
you want to resolve that for us? Or should we look it
up?
I thought that that was a pretty easy identifiable stage.
Where exactly does the 40-year gap occur?
Exactly, not so clear, right? מדין
*Midyan* is also towards the end.
It was before מדין *Midyan*.
Yeah, I mean, the next פרשה *parsha*, מרים *Miriam* dies. But right
after חוקת *Chukas*, ויבאו
בני ישראל כל העדה מדבר צין בחדש הראשון וישב העם בקדש ותמת
שם מרים *vayavo'u Bnei Yisrael kol ha-eidah midbar Tzin bachodesh ha-rishon vayeshev
ha-am b'Kadesh vatamot sham Miriam*. Or maybe it was given at הר
סיני and then, all
right,
but that’s not what תוספות Tosafot assumes. Okay? So therefore דסלקא דעתך
אמינא אדם כי ימות באהל מפרשה זו ואילך. So this is a
really great question: What is the status of people that had this
state before it was legislated, right? So and here what we’re learning
out קבר לפני הדבור kever lifnei hadibbur is, yes, these הלכות halachos
actually do apply. If you got into that condition before it was
legislated, you still are טמא tamei, and you have to deal with
your state, okay? Now this actually is very interesting because תוספות Tosafot
is about to quote, we’re learning this in the morning, the whole
issue about נדה, niddah, and there’s a similar דרשה by נדה וזבה.
niddah vezavah. It says, and תוספות Tosafos is about to quote it,
it says כיוצא בזה בפרק הבא על העריות דמשכח פסוק לזב שלפני
הדבור. kiyotzei bezeh beperek haba al ha’arayot demashchach pasuk lezav shelifnei hadibbur.
איש כי יהיה זב מבשרו מכאן ואילך. ish ki yihyeh zav mibesaro
mikan va’eilach.
What if a man had a flow before פרשת זבים parshas zavim
was said? What if a woman had her period before the פרשה
of נדה niddah was said? Is she a נדה niddah once it’s
been legislated or it’s only from that moment on? Okay, so this
actually is saying though, actually, if you have this state, even if
it occurred beforehand, these הלכות halachos still apply. Which is, again, partly
might do the question of how much is this just law and
how much is it assuming that there’s a metaphysical reality here? So
you have that state and now you’re being informed what are the
relevant הלכות halachos about that state.
If what’s-his-name says the whole thing in דברים Devarim was 38 years
later. 38 years later.
Okay, so there you go. When was פרשת טומאת מת parshas tumas
meis said? I understand that the beginning of it was said in
the beginning, yeah. Yes.
So תוספות Tosafos follow the Rapoport's course because they say that part
of the תורה was after הר סיני.
Well, there’s a whole debate in the גמרא gemara. about whether מגילה
מגילה ניתנה Megillah Megillah nitnah or חתומה ניתנה. chasumah nitnah. So, you
know, I understand you’re being facetious. Okay, so now let’s continue. Back
to the גמרא.
gemara For whatever reason, we’re saying the people involved are sort of
penalized before...
Not
penalized, that’s the state that they’re in, you know. If you consider
it to be a metaphysical reality and not just a legislation, right?
So that’s different. Meaning, if you entered into a contract that before
מתן תורה we decided that, I don’t know, משיכה meshicha was קונה
koneh and after מתן תורה כסף kesef is קונה koneh or something
like that, you wouldn’t say, oh, it’s too bad, you know, somehow
that contract wasn’t binding because new law, whatever. But that’s clear only
about law. I think it’s assuming that טומאה, tumah, the interesting thing,
and I haven’t done this, I mean you could do it in
two seconds on Bar Ilan, is look for לפני הדבור, lifnei hadibbur,
look through the מדרש הלכה, does it apply this idea לרבות לפני
הדבור lerabos lifnei hadibbur in areas not related to טומאה וטהרה? tumah
vetaharah That’s I think the interesting question because by טומאה tumah וטהרה
you particularly understand that that could be something that assumes there’s a
real metaphysical reality here, right? So, yes.
And if you’re assuming a metaphysical reality then the question is,
were people, when way before, not these people who were in the
in-between state where they know what טומאה tumah was and then suddenly
they’re טומאה, tumah but like people who lived and died and do
we consider them having been
טומאה?
tumah, Yeah, but what would be like the relevance of that? Meaning
if, meaning maybe they were maybe they weren’t, but there were no
laws that attached to that reality. Now we’re saying this is a
real state that you have, right, you know, and now here are
the laws that attach to it, right?
So, I think that happens in law also. Like I like what
you did with saying metaphysical reality versus law, but I think it
also happens in law that people can be in a, their status
can change. Right.
Right, so the law can change their status, but what this is
telling you is that the law can also address a, it’s not
like the status doesn’t exist. The law could have, let me say
it this way: It could have just as easily have said we’re
not going to apply the laws to people that had the status
from beforehand. But it’s possible to apply it, but it is possible
to make the choice to apply it for those that have the
status because it’s not like the status is only created through the
law. The status does exist so the law can choose to, you
know, yeah.
It’s like welfare reform, right? Like just because
you increase the minimum wage, it doesn’t mean that the people before,
before that they were making enough money and now they’re not.
But again, that’s because that’s all a matter of law. And that’s
why I’m saying here it’s possible to talk about about it because
we could say that even before there were any הלכות halachos of
טומאת מת tumas meis we believe that there was a metaphysical reality
that you had this טומאה tumah, that attached to you. You know,
that seems to be. So therefore we can therefore go back and
address it. All right, let’s move on.
Someone was טמא tamei. and so then and then this פרשה was
revealed, you know, 34 years later. Right. So then you go back
and you apply those הלכות halachos to that person who’s been
living...
No, they’re not held liable for I don’t know having entered the
מקדש Mikdash or doing it, they didn’t violate, but what you could
say is from this point on because you have that status right
now because you touched this dead body, these are the laws you
have to abide to from this point on.
Right, so they’d have to bring a קרבן korban let’s say or
they’d have to wait.
They'd have to wait seven days, they'd have to do the sprinkling
of פרה אדומה, parah adumah, right,
and in that reality all those laws apply.
With no relevant laws, right, and now they, but now they.
But even our own it wasn't part of his whole ritual
until like to
do the, yeah,
so
I mean obviously there was טומאת מת tumas meis, before him because
you had the whole פסח שני. Alright, let's move on. Okay, ומזה
בשלישי ובשביעי וסותר. umazeh bashlishi uvisvi'i vesoteis. So this is finally the
end of the משנה mishnah that all these things a נזיר מגלח
nazir megaleach and the relevant of a נזיר מגלח nazir megaleach is
also that you sprinkle on day three and seven if he had
these טומאות, tumos, it destroys the earlier days. And now the question
here is our גרסא girsa of that משנה mishnah, is, I'll just
go back and read the משנה. mishnah Our גרסא girsa of that
משנה mishna, is ומזה בשלישי ובשביעי umazeh bashlishi uvisvi'i
you sprinkle the ashes of the פרה אדומה parah adumah on day
three and seven, וסותר את הקודמין vesoteis es hakodmin
it destroys any earlier count, ואינו מתחיל למנות עד שיטהר ve-eino mas'chil
limnos ad she-yit-har
you only begin counting after you're טהור, tahor ומביא את קרבנותיו umeivi
es korbanosav and you bring your קרבנות. korbanos. So with that גרסא
girsa it's clear that you only begin counting on day eight. You're
טהור tahor. on day seven, you bring the קרבנות korbanos on day
eight. What becomes clear from the גמרא gemara where we're about to
read and תוספות Tosafos says this explicitly is that our גמרא Gemara
did not have the גרסא girsa ומביא את קרבנותיו. umeivi es korbanosav.
It just says ואינו מתחיל למנות עד שיטהר ve-eino mas'chil limnos ad
she-yit-har
until you become טהור. tahor, So our גמרא Gemara wants to know
what does that mean? Does it mean you start on day seven
or does it mean you start on day eight after the קרבן?
korban? So let's go back let's now look at the גמרא. Gemara
Okay, איבעיא להו, ibaya lehu, we ask, הא דקתני hadi d'katani עד
שיטהר ad she-yit-har until you become טהור, tahor. בשביעי קאי bishvi'i ka-i
עד דעביד הערב שמש, ad d'avid ha'erev shemesh, are we saying until
day seven?
ומני רבי אליעזר היא umanni Rabbi Eliezer hi and what we mean
is all you have to wait is until nightfall because then you're
totally טהור. tahor And that's רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer you might remember
earlier that says that you can start counting even before you bring
your קרבן korban once you're טהור tahor you begin your נזירות nezirus
of טהרה tahara starting on day eight because you're fully טהור tahor.
at the end of day seven, so day eight is the first
of your new נזירות nezirus of טהרה. tahara. אודלמא בשמיני קאי od
dilma bishmini ka-i or maybe we mean on day eight, דעד שיטהר
d'ad she-yit-har includes the bringing of the קרבן, korban, ומאי עד שיטהר
עד שיביא קרבנותיו umai ad she-yit-har ad she-yavi korbanosav until you bring
the קרבנות, korbanos, meaning and then you don't start counting until the
following day. ומני רבנן היא umanni Rabbanan hi and it's the Rabbis.
Okay, so which one is it? So תא שמע tash ma now
it's funny because עד שיטהר ad she-yit-har if you didn't have the
phrase ומביא את קרבנותיו, meivi korbanosav, by a נזיר טמא nazir tamei
we know that the טהרה tahara process really is done at the
end of day seven. Right, the bringing of the קרבנות korbanos you
might say you need to bring the קרבן korban to initiate the
new נזירות nezirus of טהרה, tahara, but it would be funny to
refer to that as not yet being טהור. tahor Okay, but anyway
that's the question the גמרא Gemara, raises. So let's see what the
answer is. תא שמע מדקתני סיפא tash ma midikata'ni seifa from the
end, which means the משנה mishna, we're about to read that speaks
about the things that a נזיר nazir is not מגלח megaleach for.
So the משנה mishnah, we're about to read in one second that
a נזיר nazir is not מגלח, megaleach, what does it say? מתחיל
ומונה מיד mas'chil umoneh miyad that it says that these things are,
it says you're, well we might as well look at it. Look
at the very last line of this דף, okay we won't read
the first part of the משנה, mishnah but these are a list
of things that a נזיר nazir is not מגלח. megaleach. It says
ומזה בשלישי ובשביעי umazeh bashlishi uvisvi'i you sprinkle on day three and
seven because you still have to become טהור tahor, even if you're
not מגלח megaleach you're still טמא, tamei so you do the sprinkling
of the ashes, you still have to become טהור, tahor. ואינו סותר
את הקודמין ve-eino soteir es hakodmin it doesn't destroy earlier days, ומתחיל
ומונה מיד umas'chil umoneh miyad and you begin immediately. Now what is
the immediately there? The assumption is immediately after day three and day
seven. If you're a נזיר nazir and you became טמא למת tamei
lemeis but you're not מגלח megaleach because it was, I don't know,
it was a רובע קב עצמות, rova kav atzamos, חצי קב עצמות.
khatzi kav atzamos. Fine, but you're real טומאת מת. tumas meis. It
might be you don't have to be מגלח, megaleach, it's not destroying
the earlier days, but there's an obvious taken for granted assumption you
can't count נזירות nezirus while you're טמא מת. tamei meis. Right, while
you have טומאת מת tumas meis you can't count it towards your
נזירות nezirus of טהרה. tahara. So when do you begin, are able
to start continuing to count? After you're טהור. tahor. So ומזה בשלישי
ובשביעי ומתחיל ומונה מיד. umazeh bashlishi uvisvi'i umas'chil umoneh miyad. Okay. So
what does the מיד miyad there mean? The מיד miyad there means
immediately after you become טהור. tahor, All right, is that clear?
It's clear but it's not what you'd think the word מיד. miyad.
Well, after it says wait, wait, but not after I say, if
I say look here's what you gotta do, you gotta sprinkle on
day three and seven and then you can count, begin immediately. So
then immediately means after, immediately after three and seven. Okay, that's the
way, I mean I think that's the way it's reading it. Okay
fine, that's the way it's reading it, okay and combined with the
assumption that if you're טמא מת tamei meis you can't count it
towards your נזירות nezirus of טהרה. tahara.
Right, in other words if you don't have to be מגלח megaleach
because of the nature of the טומאה, tumah
maybe there's a way
where that גרסא girsa is not connect...
I understand, I got it, I got it. But since the משנה
mishnah. is saying you מזה, mazeh, it's telling you sprinkle three and
seven and start counting immediately, the גמרא Gemara, is reasonably reading this
as... As immediately after three and seven. So if that's what it's
telling you by the case that a נזיר nazir is not מגלח,
megalei'ach, מיד miyad means right after three and seven. So when it
says by a נזיר nazir that is מגלח, megalei'ach, he doesn't begin
עד שיטהר ad she-yit-har until he becomes טהור, tahor it can't mean
right after three and seven; it seems to be saying until a
slightly later point. Is that clear? By the נזיר, nazir, right. Okay,
so therefore it says, so
the גמרא gemara. says דמכדי קתני סיפא מתחיל למנות מיד היי רישא
עד שיטהר עד שיביא קרבנותיו. dimecadani seifa mat-chil limnos miyad hai reisha
ad she-yit-har ad she-yavi korbnotav. So when it says if beginning after
day seven is called מיד, miyad, so when it says עד שיטהר,
ad she-yit-har, it can't be day seven, it must be after day
eight. So it must be until after you bring the קרבנות. korbnot.
ומני רבנן היא דאמרי נזירות טהרה עד שמיני לא חיילא, u-manni Rabbanan
hi de-amri nezirus tahara ad shemini lo chayila, that it does not
begin right until day eight. Okay. Wait, I just want to see
one thing before we continue. Hold on.
Yeah, I think I might have misstated it earlier. For the question
is, I got a little bit confused because the גמרא gemara. used
the phrase
earlier עד שיטהר בשביעי קאי עד דעביד ערב שמש, ad she-yit-har bishvii
kai ad de-avid erev shemesh, which sounds like עד שיטהר ad she-yit-har
means after ערב שמש erev shemesh until day eight. But really רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer's position, and I was just double-checking, תוספות Tosafos says
this, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer's position is day seven. The real question
is until, so it's not עד דעביד, ad de-avid, I don't understand
the phrase, it doesn't seem like תוספות Tosafos doesn't quote it, you
don't need ערב שמש erev shemesh on day seven. Basically, the position
is either you do the sprinkling on day seven and you begin
on day seven, really before you do ערב שמש, erev shemesh, that's
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer's position, and the רבנן Rabbanan's position is no,
you have to wait until you bring the קרבנות korbnot on day
eight and you begin on day eight. So the question is do
you begin on day seven or do you begin on day eight?
The phrase of עד דעביד ערב שמש, ad de-avid erev shemesh, I'm
not sure what it's doing, but תוספות Tosafos explicitly says for רבי
אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, and that's how the גמרא earlier, for רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer it's day seven, for the חכמים Chachamim it's day eight.
And that's clear from the last line of the גמרא, it says
רבנן היא דאמרי נזירות טהרה עד שמיני לא חיילא, Rabbanan hi de-amri
nezirus tahara ad shemini lo chayila, which means but on day eight
it begins. Okay. So if you say מיד miyad by the next
משנה, mishna it means you start when you're not מגלח, megalei'ach, you
start recounting on day seven; when you are מגלח megalei'ach and you
have to bring the קרבנות, korbnot, עד שיטהר ad she-yit-har means you
wait until day eight. Okay, let's now look at the next משנה,
which we've been referring to a number of times and see the
list of things that a נזיר nazir is not מגלח megalei'ach for.
Okay. אבל הסככות והפרעות, aval haschachot vehapraot, the סככות schachot and the
פרעות, praot, which we're going to see basically means the overhanging trees
and the outjutting walls, so things which rabbinically we say you cannot
walk under because we're afraid there will be an אוהל, but מדאורייתא
midoraissa it's not really a concern. Why it's not a דאורייתא doraissa
concern we'll get to in the גמרא, but that's that scenario. So
that's a type of a pseudo אוהל. So we're not talking about
the actual corpse itself or parts of the corpse, we're talking about
the ways it's being transmitted.
ובית הפרס, uveit hapras, בית הפרס Beis HaPras is a large field
that a grave had been plowed over, and the rabbis say that
for a very wide area around that field, you know, in that
field, you have to be concerned that there might be little bits
of bones. So מדאורייתא midoraissa there would be, you would not have
to be concerned because it's incorporating such a large area and so
on, and again because it's tiny little bits, it would only be
if you were to touch
them. But מדרבנן miderabbanan we say that if you go through בית
הפרס Beis HaPras you are
טמא. tamei וארץ עמים, ve'eretz amim, that's outside of ארץ ישראל. Eretz
Yisrael. We say the land outside of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael is
טמא, tamei and that could be for one of two reasons: either
because of a concern that, you know, bodies are buried all over,
which is funny because if non-Jews are not מטמא באוהל, right, who
cares if they're buried all over if you're not touching them? So
maybe it's because we're afraid the Jewish bodies were buried all over?
I mean, there's been a lot of Jewish tragedy, but still it's
an interesting question. Or what seems to be something that really factored
into this ארץ העמים, Eretz Ha'amim, and תוספות Tosafos says this explicitly,
and we'll get to this today, is a type of a
social national
legislation to try to keep people in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Okay.
So
therefore ארץ העמים Eretz Ha'amim is טמא. tamei Okay. Also it could
be a theological point, right, you know, that ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
is the only, I'm serious, it's like you know, is the land
where God is present and outside of it is an ארץ הטמאה.
eretz ha-tzmeiya. Okay. But that's all
רבני. rabbinic. והגולל והדופק. vehagolel vehadofek. גולל ודופק golel ve-dofek is an
interesting question what that means. רש"י Rashi says that means basically the
top and the sides of the coffin. Okay. Which are interesting because
we already learned that a קבר סתום is, everything is
מטמא. But here's an interesting question: as we know, there are some
things that are טומאה דאורייתא, tuma doraissa, like a half of a...
or רביעית קב עצמות, revi'is kav atzmos, and we're about to get
to other things that even if they're דאורייתא, de'oraisa, technically a נזיר's
nazir not מגלח. megale'ach. So we never have discussed the previous משנה,
this whole משנה of a נזיר מגלח nazir megale'ach didn't tell you
what happens if he touches a קבר not opposite the מת meis,
itself, right? We just discussed a קבר סתום, right? So what if
you have, I don't know, let's say
a קבר, you mean like the coffin?
The coffin, the coffin. Here you've got a coffin, right, and you've
got this מת, meis, right, and a נזיר nazir just touches this
part of it, okay? So what's the story? He's not מאהיל ma'ahil
on the מת, meis he's only טמא tamei because או בקבר. קבר
סתום, is that included in the list of נזיר מגלח? nazir megale'ach?
All right, we don't, right, it was not in the previous משנה.
So and there are things that are טומאה דאורייתא tumah de'oraisa that
the נזיר's nazir not מגלח. megale'ach. So רש״י Rashi reads the גולל
ודופק golel v'dofek as basically the the
sideboards and the top of the coffin. תוספות Tosafos. disagrees.
Is it certainly the bottom?
Yeah, תוספות Tosafos disagrees and תוספות Tosafos. says that from other גמרות
gemaros it sounds clear that these are things that are above ground.
So תוספות Tosafos, says the גולל ודופק golel v'dofek is the the
tombstone and if they had like supporting stones that were to help
keep it up, like you know so it wouldn't fall, that's the
גולל ודופק. golel v'dofek. And that that also we learn from, and
one of the places this is learned from is על פני השדה.
al pnei hasadeh. Before we learned that it's טומאת אהל, tumah ohel,
but there's another דרשה that says basically, and that's why תוספות tosafos
says it looks like it's above ground, something of the מת meis.
that remains above ground, something that represents the מת. meis So it's
the tombstone and the supporting stones. And the fact is a טומאה
דאורייתא tumah de'oraisa but never and טומאת מת דאורייתא, tumas meis de'oraisa,
but nevertheless not נזיר מגלח. nazir megale'ach. Somehow we learned that that's
not in the list of נזיר מגלח. nazir megale'ach. Like in catacombs?
Yeah, that's a good question, you know, that's a very good point.
Yeah, but תוספות Tosafot is making a claim about the מדרש הלכה.
Well the point is they did a re-inter... and they re-inter... no
they did a burial in ground and then a re-interment in the
catacombs. But that's a good question. Would they do... oh you mean
like the the stone that would seal the catacombs maybe? That's interesting.
I don't know what תוספות Tosafot would say to this.
ש״ס Shas has a photograph of such a stone.
A stone that seals the catacomb. Oh I see, oh that's nice,
so it's over there. Well there you go, so maybe that's that's
a good, that's a third interpretation. We'll have to add that into
the תוספות. No I'm saying that actually makes a lot of sense.
Maybe תוספות would have said that it's for the burial prior to
the re-interment but they'd still have to put up a tombstone, I
guess they needed a tombstone so they would know where to go
back to. Okay, let's, I mean if you want to take a
look, let's look at the short תוספות. הגולל והדופק. hagolel v'hadofek. תוספות,
פירש רש״י בפרק קמא דכתובות, peirush Rashi b'perek kama d'Kesubos, גולל זה
כיסוי ארון golel zeh kisui aron ודופק הוא הדופן של הצדדים. v'dofek
hu hadofen shel hatzedadim. Okay. והקשה רבינו תם דאמרינן בפרק במה מדליקין
על פני השדה לרבות גולל ודופק, v'hiksha Rabbeinu Tam d'amrinan b'perek Bameh
Madlikin al pnei hasadeh l'rabos golel v'dofek, משמע דגלויין הן גולל
ודופק mashma d'gluyin hein golel v'dofek
ואלו מכוסים. v'eilu mechusim. Sounds like they're exposed. פירש רבינו תם דגולל
הוא המצבה ודופק אבנים שהמצבה נשענת בהן. peirush Rabbeinu Tam d'golel hu
hamatzeiva v'dofek avanim shehamatzeiva nish'enes bahen. Okay. So
now maybe I don't know, maybe he means your interpretation which is
that the stone is, but I don't think he's calling the sealing
stone the מצבה. matzeiva. So maybe he's being, maybe he's being anachronistic
you know but or maybe it's the where they were buried before
they were re-interred. It's a very good point.
I think the חז״ל Chazal call a tombstone a ציון. tziyun. Right.
ובנה עליו ציון, u'vanah alav tziyun, it's a פסוק actually.
Right, right, exactly.
In other words it marks the place where you know not to
walk. Right, right.
I mean now that Rabbi David was reminding me and there's explicit
look. Yeah, I mean I don't know yeah clearly like the whole
idea clearly there were burials underground. I mean the whole discussion here
that we just did about a בית הפרס, beis hapras, which is
a concern about a grave that was plowed or all the גמרות
gemaros are going to talk about that when you dig and you
find a grave and you have to be concerned that there's a
graveyard. So clearly you know and that's in the משניות, mishnayos, right?
So I don't know enough about that right but I was blanking
on that for a moment but clearly both phenomena were present. You
know there's a lot of examples about right and about מציין את
הקברות metzayein es hakevaros and all that so there definitely was burial
in... royalty really put in sarcophagi?
Right, it could be, right, exactly. It could be it could be
it had to have a certain amount, right, if you could afford
it or something. All right, we have to look into that more
but it's a very good point but clearly there were both phenomena.
Okay, alright so both above ground and below. Okay,
all
right. So that is but important is now we're introducing something that
is דאורייתא de'oraisa but that is not נזיר מגלח. nazir megale'ach. And
now we do the other things that we have mentioned, רביעית דם.
revi'is dam. A רביעית revi'is of דם dam which is דאורייתא de'oraisa
and a נזיר nazir is not מגלח. megale'ach. Okay, and that would
be whether touch or אהל. ohel Anything... דם dam is... there's no
difference between touching and אהל. ohel, It's a רביעית דם revi'is dam
for טומאה tumah but a חצי לוג chatzi log for מגלח. megale'ach.
And אוהל רובע עצמות. ohel rova atzmos. It should be a ו,
vov, ואוהל רובע עצמות. v'ohel rova atzmos. And an אהל ohel. for
a רובע עצמות. rova atzmos. So a רובע עצמות rova atzmos which
is the quarter of a... קב kav of עצמות atzmos causes טומאת
אהל. ohel So yes, you are טמא tamei דאורייתא de'oraita טומאת מת,
tumas meis, but you're not מגלח megale'ach unless you are an אהל
ohel with a חצי chatzi קב kav עצמות. atzmos. So this is
the
implicit other side of the coin of what we did yesterday, of
what we've been doing the last few days. Okay, that these things
are טומאה tumah, דאורייתא, de'oraita, דם dam by touch and אהל, ohel
this amount, and bones by אהל. ohel, But even though it's טומאה
tumah דאורייתא, de'oraita, not נזיר nazir מגלח. megale'ach. So now we've got
those things. The lesser amount of דם dam and of bones is
דאורייתא, de'oraita, not מגלח, megale'ach, and the גולל golal and דופק. dofek.
And now we get to a very interesting next category which gets
back to our earlier פסוק, right. וכלים הנגועים במת. Ve-keilim hanog'im be-meis.
Okay, vessels that touch the dead body. So, what are we talking
about? So we could be talking about, first we could be talking
about that we don't know of any הלכה of חרב הרי הוא
כחלל, cherev ha-rei ke-chalal, or we don't know, or this is not
חרב הרי הוא כחלל, cherev ha-rei ke-chalal, however we define it, and
it's just a normal vessel that touches a dead body. Okay, but
then that's pretty boring because then the vessel touches the dead body,
the vessel is an אב, av, the person who touches it is
a ראשון, rishon, and that's not טומאת מת. tumas meis. טומאת מת
tumas meis. that destroys נזירות nezirus is a seven-day טומאה, tumah right,
is when the נזיר nazir becomes an אב, av not when the
נזיר nazir becomes a ראשון. rishon. So it's much more interesting if
we assume that these are the vessels that fall into the category
of חרב הרי הוא כחלל cherev ha-rei ke-chalal and the חרב is
considered an אבי אבות like the מת meis itself, and the נזיר
nazir touches it, and the נזיר nazir is an אב and it's
a seven-day טומאה, tumah. and even though it's a seven-day טומאה tumah.
because it is one of those things that is
not in the primary list, then even though it's a טומאה tumah,
דאורייתא, de'oraita, it is not standard enough or not classic enough for
a נזיר nazir to be מגלח. megale'ach. Okay, this is very relevant,
I'll just tell you now why, when we get to it, it's
not today, we'll get tomorrow, so you should be happy, we're slowing
down a little bit so we're not going to be so far
ahead, but we'll get to it tomorrow to discuss what exactly is
in the category of חרב הרי הוא כחלל. cherev ha-rei ke-chalal. Okay,
but assuming that we're saying that a חרב הרי הוא כחלל cherev
ha-rei ke-chalal is a, it's that it could be a full טומאה,
tuma אבי אבות הטומאה avi avos hatumah. like the מת meis, itself,
and nevertheless it's excluded that a נזיר nazir is not מגלח. megale'ach.
So if a נזיר nazir is not מגלח, megale'ach, that also would
mean that a כהן kohein is not מוזהר muzhar עליו alav because
there's a line in מסכת שמחות maseches smachot which we פוסקין pasken
by: כל מת שאין הנזיר מגלח עליו אין כהן מוזהר עליו. kol
meis she'ein hanazir megale'ach alav, ein kohein muzhar alav. Okay, now, normally
who cares? Meaning what are the things we've excluded here? דרבננס, derabbanans,
which okay clearly they're not
דאורייתא, de'oraita, רוב עצמות, rov atzmot, רביעית דם, revi'is dam, that's not
going to help a כהן kohein too much. Okay, interestingly, according to
רש״י Rashi though, I should say what might help a כהן kohein
is the גולל ודופק. golal ve-dofek. Because if the coffin is not
מוזהר muzhar עליו, alav, if a נזיר nazir is not מגלח megale'ach
and according is not מוזהר muzhar on the coffin only on the
מת, meis this leads to very interesting questions we discussed, right? Would
you therefore say that you could be מאהיל m'ahil over the whole
thing, that it's מפסיק? mafsik?
You can go to cemeteries?
Or is it only touching he's not מוזהר, muzhar, but if he's
מאהיל m'ahil over it? I don't know. Okay, right. But so that's
one thing. But in terms of the וכלים הנגועים במת, ve-keilim hanog'im
be-meis, if it's talking about a חרב הרי הוא כחלל, cherev ha-rei
ke-chalal, okay wonderful, so a כהן kohein can touch something that was
in the same אהל ohel of a מת meis, or that touched
a מת, meis, who cares? What does that do for him? Okay,
so here I want to tell you about a brilliant solution which
רב משה Rav Moshe had a fit about, but that yeah about
about that רב הרצוג Rav Herzog had for dealing with this issue.
No, wasn't רב הרצוג, Rav Herzog, no it was רב גורן, Rav
Goren, excuse me, רב גורן Rav Goren had for dealing with the
problem of can a כהן kohein study medicine to become a doctor
and become טמא tamei למת? la-meis? So you remember we learned,
a few weeks ago that if a, that other than the position
of the ראב״ד, Ra'avad, that even though we assume כהנים kohanim are
טמאי מת, tmei meis, that they can't become re-טמא tamei because they're
raising the level of טומאה tumah when they come in contact, they're
now their level of טומאה tumah is higher. First of all, if
they became טמא tamei. למת la-meis a week ago, they're more in
the process of becoming טהור tahor, now just because they could be
more ready for the אפר efer of פרה אדומה. parah adumah. But
even besides that, their level is lower because when you're actively touching
a מת, meis it raises the level of your טומאה. tumah So
רב גורן Rav Goren said, here's what we're going to do. We're
going to go ahead and take some metal pins, and you like
a little pin or whatever, or rings or whatever they're going to
be, and you bring them into a room and where there's a
dead body. Now all these rings are חרב הרי הוא כחלל, cherev
ha-rei ke-chalal, they're as just as טמא as the מת meis itself.
But a כהן kohein is not prohibited to touch them if a
נזיר nazir is not מגלח. megale'ach. So then have כהנים wear these
rings. Now they are actively touching, see, so if I was wearing,
if this was my ring that was in the אהל ohel, of
a dead body, okay, I am now actively touching something that is
as טמא as the מת mes itself, right? Because this ring is
like an אבי אבות הטומאה. So now if I'm handling a dead
body, I'm not raising my level of טומאה. tumah So therefore even
though I'm not allowed to become טמא to the dead body, it's
not a problem if it's not raising the level of טומאה, tumah
and I was allowed to put on the ring because I'm not
מוזהר muzhar on something that is
a
כהן... kohein... It has some relevance to a כהן. kohein.
Is it like your nose going into the room first? You have
to put your nose with the ring into the doorway first?
No, once you're, no, no. Anyway, fine. Okay, so anyway that is
a list, so what's really interesting there is גולל ודופק golel v'dofek
on the one hand, which could be a דאורייתא, de'oraisa, and נזיר
לא מגלח, nazir lo megaleiach, and כלים הנוגעים במת keilim hanogaim b'meis
which presumably is חרב כחלל cherev k'chalal that even though it causes
טומאת מת, tumas meis, it's not מגלח. megaleiach. We'll see more about
that. And now we deal with things that are not even
טומאת מת. tumas meis, ובימי ספרו ובימי גמרו. u'bimei seforo u'bimei gmaro.
If he is a מצורע metzora and he is the days of
counting and the days of completing. What does that mean? So somebody
has a spot and they're not sure whether it's צרעת, tzaraas, and
the כהן kohein comes and shuts them up and says we'll look
at it again in seven days. Okay. We're going to see in
a minute that is a period actually which is referred later in
the משנה as ימי הסגרו, yimei hesgeiro, okay, the days of being
shut up and quarantined for a week. That period, okay, we'll get
to that in a minute. After that period, the כהן kohein comes
back and the spot has spread. So now I'm a מצורע. metzora.
But now actually he shuts me up another seven days for to
see if what will continue, but it's this stage that it's already
gotten worse after the first week, that's called ימי גמרו, yimei gmaro,
okay, that I am now like, you know, that I'm sort of
closed up as it were and finished and becoming that. Now after
it has actually cleared and I call back the כהן kohein and
he sees that it's cleared, and then we go through this process
of טהרה, tahara, that's like a seven-day process. On the eighth day
I bring my קרבן, korban, that's
called ימי ספרו. yimei seforo. So ימי ספרו וימי גמרו, yimei seforo
u'bimei gmaro, it's interesting, it's like the reverse chronological order, are the
days where the guy is already definitely a מצורע metzora at the
sort of full level, but he is, you know, continuing to sort
of observe the spread of the problem or he's in the process
of becoming טהור, tahor. but he's a full-level מצורע. metzora. Okay, so
in those days, even though he's a full-level מצורע, metzora, he is
it does not he's not מגלח megaleiach because it's not טומאת מת.
tumas meis. על אלו אין הנזיר מגלח, al eilu ein hanazir megaleiach,
he doesn't shave. ומזה בשלישי ובשביעי, u'mazah bashlishi u'bashvii, he sprinkles three
and seven for the טומאת מת, mes not for the מצורע metzora
case, obviously. ואינו סותר את הקודמים. v'eino soiser es hakodmim. It does
not destroy any earlier days yet. Even though it's טומאת מת, mes?
it doesn't destroy earlier days because of these exceptions. ומתחיל ומנה מיד
u'maschil u'moneh miyad and again, the way we just read it is,
okay, it doesn't destroy the earlier days, but he has to wait
until to continue counting until he becomes טהור. tahor. Okay. וקרבן אין
לו, v'korban ein lo, he doesn't bring a קרבן. korban. Now, ובאמת
אמרו, u'be'emes amru, in truth they said,
ימי הזב והזבה, yimei hazav v'hazava, if the person isn't a מצורע,
metzora, person's only a זב zav or זבה, zava, or ימי הסגרו
של מצורע, yimei hesgeiro shel metzora, to a מצורע metzora but it's
in the first week when we're first monitoring the spread, in those
cases הרי אלו עולים לו. harei eilu olin lo. They even count
towards the towards,
you know, he can even count those days towards his נזירות neziros
days. Now the normal response would be well like obviously he's not
טמא מת, tamei meis, right? We never saw that any other טומאה
is a contradiction. So the only so that is it should be
obvious. The real חידוש chiddush. here is what it implies about the
first line, when it says ומתחיל ומנה מיד, u'maschil u'moneh miyad, right?
Which means he's מתחיל maschil he begins to continue counting after he's
טהור. tahor It basically means that for the מצורע metzora that is
a more weighty מצורע metzora that's not in the first week, he
can only continue counting after he gets out of his צרעת tzaraas
state. Right? You understand? Because it contrasted the weighty מצורע metzora who
it says he that he begins counting after he becomes טהור tahor
to says but if he's a זב zav or she's a זבה
zava or it's a מצורע metzora in the first week, then they
can even count those days. Okay, so there's a real so again,
that's not a big חידוש. chiddush It's not טומאת מת. mes. The
real חידוש chiddush. is the first point, which is you don't count
it's you if you're טמא מת, tamei meis, even if it's not
even if it's not מגלח, megaleiach, you don't count those days, that's
not a big חידוש. But if you're a מצורע metzora and you're
in the second week or the third week or whatever, you're more
than the first week of a מצורע, metzora, even those days you
can't count towards your נזירות. neziros. Not clear why. We'll have to
see about that in the גמרא. Okay, so let's take a look.
What time is it? Well we still no. Okay, alright, let's just
read let's just read one line, one or two lines of the
גמרא. ואלו הן הסככות. v'eilu hen hascachoch. Here's the סככות. scachoch. אילן
המיסך על הארץ. ilan hamaysach al ha'aretz. A tree that's overshadowing on
the on the land. ופראות, u'peravos, and פראות peravos are היוצאות מן
הגדר, hayotzos min hageder, אבנים היוצאות מן הגדר, avanim hayotzos min hageder,
stones that come out from a גדר. geder. We think of it
as a fence but it really means like a wall. Okay, now,
and you walked under those. Now why are those only rabbinic problems?
So let's take a look at תוספות and we'll end with it.
אילן
המיסך על הארץ. ilan hamaysach al ha'aretz. בפרק קמא דנידה אמרינן, b'perek
kama d'nida amrinan, דמדאורייתא לאו אהל מעליא. d'mide'oraisa lav ohel maalya. It's
not a real אהל ohel biblically. שהנפים רחוקים זה מזה she'hanafim rechokim
zeh mizeh ואין בהם פותח טפח. v'ein bahem poseiach tefach. That the
trees or the branches are spread out, so you don't really have
a טפח tefach by
a
טפח tefach of solid. solid טפח tefach I mean with the leaf,
you have
to depend on how thick the branches are, how big the leaves
are. So it's a case where it's not a real דאורייתא de-Oraisa
problem. Okay. אף כי יש ודאי כזית מן המת תחת אחת מהן,
Af ki yesh vadai ke-zayis min ha-mes tachas achas me-hen, there is
a מת mes buried under one of them, ומן התורה טהור, u-min
ha-Torah tahor, biblically you're טהור tahor if you walked under because you
really weren't under a real דאורייתא אהל, de-Oraisa ohel, כי הלכת תחת
כולם, ki halachta tachas kulam, even if you went under all of
them you'd be טהור tahor, because you were never under anything that
was a real אהל, ohel, or maybe it was a ספק sefeik
and it was a רשות הרבים, reshus ha-rabim, but it's not clearly
an אהל ohel, here. ורבנן הוא דגזרו טומאה בהולך תחתיהן, Ve-rabbanan hu
de-gazru tumah be-holeich tachtehen, and it's all rabbinic. So that's the case
of the tree. What's the case about the wall? ופרועות אבנים היוצאות
מן הגדר, U-pruos avanim ha-yotzos min ha-geder, הסמוך לבית הקברות, ha-samuch le-veis
ha-kevaros,
it's a wall near a cemetery, ויש שם נפל תחת אחת
מן האבנים, ve-yesh sham nefel tachas achas min ha-avanim, there's a fetus
buried under one of them. I assume the reason he has to
say fetus is because if you think about it, if there's a
wall, right, I mean, what's the case? If there's a tree, right,
and here's your cemetery and here's your קבר, and you're walking under
here, you could sort of imagine, right, that the טומאה goes like
with the canopy, if it's the roof, the טומאה can transfer, right,
from one side of the tree to next, certainly it will transfer
on this side of the tree. But if it's a wall, right,
if there's a wall and the בית הקברות beis ha-kevaros is here,
even if the stones are outcropping, how does the טומאה get over
the wall? Right? I mean, what would be, you understand?
So you'd have to be on the side where the מת is
buried. But what are you doing on the side of the cemetery?
Right?
So that's what both parts are outcropping from the wall.
Yeah, but even if it's outcropping, the wall is what's keeping it
up. Right?
Why assume it's the cemetery? A random place?
Well, I'm just saying תוספות describes it, הסמוך לבית הקברות. ha-samuch le-veis
ha-kevaros. You don't have to say, but if you are saying it,
right, yeah, even if you have the wall sort of sticking out,
right, I'm at my 3D drawing here, right, like that, how's the
טומאה right because it's not like a tree is a thin thing
that's supporting it so the טומאה can get around, right? I mean,
if you had an overhang like this it could get around, and
maybe that is what we're talking about. That's why I don't think
that תוספות said that there's an infant, like maybe they bury, you
know, the normal מתים meisim in the cemetery, and they bury the
fetuses right in the wall outside. That's why I'm imagining he's talking
about it being a fetus to explain how are you on the
same side of the מת? Now, you didn't have to say it
was a cemetery, but that's what he's saying. Okay. ויש שם נפל,
Ve-yesh sham nefel, וגזרו חכמים טומאה למהלך תחת אחת מן האבנים, ve-gazru
chachamim tumah le-mahaleich tachas achas min ha-avanim, אף על פי שספק טומאה
ברשות הרבים ספיקו טהור. af al pi she-sefeik tumah bi-reshus ha-rabim sefeiko
tahor. And
here he says a stone is a real אהל, but the question
is you don't know if there's a fetus buried there, I mean
maybe that would be a practice sometimes they would but you don't
know for exactly that they did. So technically ספק טומאה ברשות הרבים
sefeik tumah bi-reshus ha-rabim is טהור, but דרבנן derabbanan we consider you
טמא.
Okay, it's a ספק, sefeik,
you don't know whether you walked under the same place,
not that the בנין binyan was not exactly,
but by the tree it is that the אהל is not an
אהל, and here it's that you don't know if there's a מת.
So whether you don't know about the מת or whether it's not
a clear אהל, it's only
rabbinic, and that's why נזיר Nazir is not מגלח, megaleiach, and tomorrow
we'll turn to the more interesting cases, I mean they're all interesting,
excuse me, we'll turn to the other interesting cases of
ארץ העמים, eretz ha-amim, בית הפרס, beis ha-peras, כחרב כחלל, ke-cherev ke-chalal,
it'll be a lot of fun. See you tomorrow.